<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An instruccyon of Christen fayth howe to be bolde vp on the promyse of God and not to doubte of our saluacyon, made by Urbanus Regius. Tra[n]slated into englyshe</title>
            <title>Instruccyon of Christen fayth howe to be bolde up on the promyse of God and not to doubte of our salvacyon.</title>
            <author>Rhegius, Urbanus, 1489-1541.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10577</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20847</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104513</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840249</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840249</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4729</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10577)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4729)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 142:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An instruccyon of Christen fayth howe to be bolde vp on the promyse of God and not to doubte of our saluacyon, made by Urbanus Regius. Tra[n]slated into englyshe</title>
                  <title>Instruccyon of Christen fayth howe to be bolde up on the promyse of God and not to doubte of our salvacyon.</title>
                  <author>Rhegius, Urbanus, 1489-1541.</author>
                  <author>Foxe, John, 1516-1587.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[78] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Hugh Syngelton at the singne [sic] of saynt Augustine in Paules churche yerde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Prynted at Lo[n]do[n] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1548?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date and translator's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E (-E8, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Faith --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4729:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4729:1"/>
            <p>An Inſtruccy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſten fayth howe to be bolde vp on the promyſe of God and not to doubte of our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon / made by Vrbanus Regius. Tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlated into englyſhe.</p>
            <p>Prynted at Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by Hugh Syngelton at the ſingne of ſaynt Auguſtine in Paules chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che yerde.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4729:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4729:2"/>
            <head>To his reuerende &amp; ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler good father Ric. Melton / the tranſlatour wyſſheth grace and com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fort in Chryſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N ſo moche al the effecte and ſumme of our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion conſyſteth only vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on fayth and knowlage of the ſonne of God Ieſu Chriſt, all the ſcriptures and prophetes berynge wytnes, I thynke it moch expedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t euery chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man to be well inſtructed, and traded herein, for the lacke wherof, we may ſee what great and lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes is fallen amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt vs chriſten men, howe pytu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly we wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der abowt lyke ſtray ſhepe, as the prophete ſayth, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine of our ſaluation, howe dyſcomfortly we lyue, how deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratly
<pb facs="tcp:4729:3"/> we dye, not knowi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g which way to goo / howe ignorat how fleſhly we be with out all ioy, all comfort all feelyng of the ſpiritt, with out all the trewe charite to our neighbours. For how can we loue oure neighbour trewly for gods ſake whan we nether know nor feele howe god louyth vs. Whych thyngs verely declare y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue but litell faith in vs. For els, hauyng ſo many and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt promiſes of god for our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation in the fyrſt teſtament, and the ſame alſo fulfylled ſo verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly in the latter teſtament by the commyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne of god, how culde we lyue in ſuche perplexite &amp; doubtfulnes as we do, yf there were any knowlege or fayth in vs? What co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teineth the old teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but only promiſes? Where vpon be theſe promiſes groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded? vpon the law? How ſo, were
<pb facs="tcp:4729:3"/> not theſe promiſes made to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam and to Abraham frely long before the lawe came, as ſcripture wytneſſeth .iiii. c. yeres and .xxx.<note place="margin">Gal. 3.</note> And why then do we not beleue God? Why do we yet ſtand in fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>are and doubt of oure ſaluation, as though we had no promiſes, but only our owne deſeruynges to ſtay vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Is god a diſſembler? Why than do we not ſtablyſh our hartes at the promiſe of the lorde, and reioyſe with faythful Paule triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phyng boldly agaynſt all the gates of hell? With hym ſayng, who ſhall ſeparat vs from the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue of god, any afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> any vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, any perſecution, other hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, or nakednes other any Ieo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perdy, or ſworde? No ſayth he, thys I knowe &amp; am full ſuer that nether deah, nor lyfe, nether An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel, prynce or pouer, nether thyng preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, nor thyng to come, heyght,
<pb facs="tcp:4729:4"/> nor depthe, nor no other creature ſhall be able to ſeparat me from the loue of god which is in Chriſt Ieſu our lorde. Here we may ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne the example of a faythful hart. Abraham likwiſe heryng the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of god,<note place="margin">Gen. 15.</note> that in his old age he ſhuld haue a childe, howe firmely beleued he the lord, and the lorde dyd impute yt to hym for ryghtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſnes,<note place="margin">Oculi do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piciunt fi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dem.</note> for he deliteth in nothyng ſo much as in our faith vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym. Nowe wether was it more harde for Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to haue a child ſo old, or for vs to be ſaued after our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ath &amp; trobele. And yet Abraham beleued the lord. And why do not we beleue hym as bouldly in our promiſes?<note place="margin">Luc. 1.</note> Mary heryng the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis of god beleued the angel put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge no doubt as zacharei dyd, that ſhe ſhuld haue a child a vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, and yet myght that ſeme as harde to her as thys to vs but
<pb facs="tcp:4729:4"/> what ſayd the angell, No worde or promis is harde to god. And why do not we as wel take a bold confidence hauyng ſo many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes mayde to vs in all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes? What dyd Chriſte more commend in hys confeſores than faith?<note place="margin">Luc. 7.</note> or wherin was he more an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grye with hys apoſtles,<note place="margin">Luc. 26.</note> than for their weyke faith after ſo muche hearyng &amp; ſeyng? Howbeit to ſay the truythe it is not ſo greatly to be merueled in vs, for how can we beleue the promiſes of god whan we know them not? or how ſhuld we knowe them whan we haue neither bibles to rede them, nor here them, neither be they opened vnto vs? And how can ſuch miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries be opened of the preſtes, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo many runne &amp; ſo few inſtructed and ſent of god? Wherfore in this part to helpe the ignorance and weyknes of my brithre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for a more
<pb facs="tcp:4729:5"/> ſtyrynge vppe of theyr faith, I thought it not vnprofitable to tranſlate this golden boke of Vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banus regius a moſt chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, very fruytful for euery chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man, the which booke I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend and committe vniuerſally to the whole englyſh congregation, and namly ſend it to you (moſte reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend father (both to declare ſome token of my obedient dwety to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward you, and alſo to miniſter to you ſome occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of further know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lege and conſolation whiche I moſt hartely deſire in the Lord. Grace be with you and with all the congregacion. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>By your ſone moſt bound I. Fox.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:4729:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ruly it is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uylliſhe errour to teache, that we ſhulde euer doubt, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be ſuer of Gods fauoure and our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon / as we haue ben ledde in the popes church, by vnlerned preſtes which for their purpoſe haue wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kedly wraſted the wordes of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamon in a wrong vnderſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng.<note place="margin">Eccle. 9. The He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew text meneth a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>other th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge, and is wrong tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lated.</note> Neſcit homo amore, an odio dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ſit. That is to ſay. No man can tell whether he be worthy of loue or hatred. This error hath Sathan brought in to the church to obſcure Chriſte, and cleane to abolyſh oure faith in him, and in the place of oure faith to bryng in waueryng and doubtful opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; weake imaginations in to oure myndes whereby in great extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite,
<pb facs="tcp:4729:6"/> and erneſt temptationes we could take no aſurance, but were dryuen to deſperation, for he that doubteth of the wyl and fauore of god,<note place="margin">A trewe chriſten man dou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tethe not of Gods fauour.</note> and is not aſſuered that he wyll be mercyful to hym for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes ſake / and that all his ſynnes be pardoned in hym, he is no trew chriſtiane, and in hys incredulite can not be but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned. Suer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the faith<note place="margin">Fayth.</note> in Chriſte is only that maketh a trew chriſten ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / doubt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyng &amp; incredulite<note place="margin">Incredu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie.</note> makyth a man no chriſtiane. To belue &amp; to doubt be not both on. To beleue is an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thyng than to doubt. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he that continueth in this for ſayde error, beleuyth not the .xii. articles of oure crede, catholyke faith / in the which godes grace is clerly and vndoubtedly gyuen to vs in Chriſt. Then howe can they be chriſten men whyche lacke the faith of Chriſt. Or how can ſuche
<pb facs="tcp:4729:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> one ſaye the lordes oration well? He may with hys mouthe ſounde the wordes, O oure heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but hys hart hath no truſte in god, neyther hathe any firmite that he is a mercifull father, but doubtyth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of god, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be mercyfull or no, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he pardone hym or no. His tonge ſayth I beleue in Ieſus Chriſt, I beleue the forgiuenes of ſinnes, but his hart beleuyth not that Chriſte dyed for oure offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and that by his deth he hath obtayned for vs forgyuenes of all oure ſinnes. He that waueryth thus, can not but deſpayre in the laſte extremite of hys lyfe. And yf he dyſpayre, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is he damned, for he deperteth with an euyl conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; hath no knowlege of Chriſt, nor beleuyth the goſpell. Then what hope can he haue of euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting lyfe? Yet our blynd gydes
<pb facs="tcp:4729:7"/> and ſeducers in the popes clargy haue taught vs that no man can preciſely knowe whether he be in godes fauor or no. They that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne in this error, what beleue had they? dyd they not wander lyke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wynde nowe hether and thether? were they not cleane voyde of fayth? had they not a wretched, vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>certayne, and a wauerynge lyfe? howe could they knowe whether theſe workes pleaſed God or no? what coulde this man thynke in hym ſelfe but thus? I am a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened man, I haue ſtudyed to lyue well and to do good workes, but yet I am vncerteyne whether my workes pleaſe God, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther my ſynnes be forgyuen me or not. Myne yll dedes be mo the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my good, I haue done mo ſynnes than vertues. Alas what ſhall be come of me. They that thus wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer &amp; doubt, what hope can they
<pb facs="tcp:4729:7"/> haue in the agony of death, what fayth haue they, what thynge to truſt vpon? Satan and his owne conſcience accuſe hym of ſynne, ſayenge, he that lyueth yll ſhallbe damned, thou neuer fulfylledeſt yet the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes of God, No ſynner can be ſaued. Dothe not Chriſt ſaye, yf thou wylt enter into lyfe kepe the commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes? but thou haſt neuer kept the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Mat. 19.</note> Here is no hope lefte but that a man oppreſſed with ſuche cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions, muſt nedes deſpayre. The blynde papiſtes haue taught vs poore wretches, that the fundaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of oure hope lyeth in the grace of God,<note place="margin">The doct<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryne of the preſts clargie.</note> and in the merytes of our owne workes / ſo that oure hope ſhulde be nothynge elles but the expectacion of lyfe commynge of Gods grace and of our owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruynges.<note place="margin">what ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe is by the ſophi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſters.</note> Item that our hope in no wyſe could ſtande without the
<pb facs="tcp:4729:8"/> helpe of our merites / other of the ſophiſters doo thus defyne it, hope is a boldenes of mynde conceyued of Goddes good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to haue euerlaſtynge lyfe through oure good workes. Here thou hereſt theſe two, grace and deſeruynge, but theſe two do yll ioyne together, for where is grace there is no meretynge, agayne where meretynge is there is no grace. Therfore yf a ſeke perſone tempted about his ſynnes thinke thus that without his owne me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites he can loke for no ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then he truſteth not to the grace of God, neyther doth he apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d it nor grounde hym ſelfe vpon it, for ſo he hath ben taught and led that it was preſumpcion to ſaye a man myght be aſſuerid of Gods fauour without the addynge to of his workes and merites: And thus haue we be led in this falſe
<pb facs="tcp:4729:8"/> perſuaſion ſo many yeares, but in erneſte tentacions there is none that can ſtande vpon his merites or dedes / for here commyth in the law of god accuſyng hym and all other men, that none of them all haue fulfylled yt. Then where be the good dedes, wherupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſeke man may truſte, and hope for ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation therby. In our great ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations we all do fele that we be ſynners, and that all oure lyfe is nought and ſo voyde of all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that it is not able to abyde or ſtande in the ſeuere iudgement of god. Theſe blynd ſeducers haue made one fote of oure hope lame &amp; mayned, which is grace. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fote lame and haltyng, which is our owne workes, Now howe can oure hope ſtand faſt, that we faule not in to deſperation? To proue than that by oure dedes we can deſerue no iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nether
<pb facs="tcp:4729:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> any part therof, with al that euer we are able to do, Alſo that it is not in oure pouer to accompleſhe the lawe of god,<note place="margin">The law</note> but that law only ſeruyth to ſe our vnablenes, oure vices &amp; ſynnes therby, it nedyth no great declaratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. We ſee thys dayly in our ſelues, that our fleſh neuer ceaſyth feyghtyng agaynſt the ſpiritt, &amp; doth inwardly gru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge at euery good dede we doo, ſo that this noughtines and corrup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of ours marryth all, wherby our good workes can not be pure nor acceptable that we doo. Ro. vii. Gal. v..i. Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. i. Wherfore wryteth Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yf we ſay we haue no ſyne,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 1</note> we deceiue our ſelues, &amp; truthe is not in vs. Alſo all the faythfull ſaye dayly in the lordes prayer. Forgiue vs our treſpaſſes Eſa. lxiiii.<note place="margin">Eſai. 64</note> we be as vnclene euery one, and all our ryghtuuſnes lyke a clothe defyled with the flowers
<pb facs="tcp:4729:9"/> of a woman. Forthermore yf we dyd fulfyll all commandmentes of god, yet dyd we nothyng but which is our bound deuty to doe, nether can we loke for any reward therby, wytnes to Chriſte.<note place="margin">Luc. 17.</note> Luc. xvii. Whan ye haue done all that you can, yet ſaye you be vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſaruantes. Theſe wordes of Chriſt verely may plucke downe our glory, and make vs all aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that we put no affia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in our ſelues, nor in our owne good wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes.<note place="margin">Good workes.</note> Howbeit I ſpeke not this to extenuat the worthynes of good workes, or to plucke men backe from wel doyng. For the ſcripture teachith vs, that the ſtudy of good workes is euer to be employed, &amp; wylles vs to be folowers of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty and good workyng. But no man muſte put affiaunce in hys workes, as though by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he could obtayne gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce,
<pb facs="tcp:4729:10"/> or put away ſyn or gett his ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. For yf our ryghtuouſnes and iuſtification before god ſtand in our myght or merites, than dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Chriſt in vayne. Gal. ii.<note place="margin">Gal. 2.</note> Good workes in their degree and order haue their valewe, and be great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded. A good man ought to inſewe good vertues, to thentent he may do the wyl of his lord god, whyche commaundyth vs to lyue vertuouſly, and that he may alſo approue him ſelfe to his lord god, that god our heauenly father may be glorifyed therby. Mat. v.<note place="margin">Mat. 5.</note> Alſo we ought to doo good workes, to ſhew our ſelfes thankfull agayne to God, for his infinite benefites and gyftes. Phi. ii.<note place="margin">Phil. 2.</note> Alſo we muſt do good workes to exerciſe oure faith, that they may be teſtimones of oure beleue, and thus do they profyt both me and my neybour. My neyghbour in gyuyng exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple
<pb facs="tcp:4729:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> to encorage hym the better to a chriſtiane lyfe. Alſo in that he is ſuccored by them in his neceſſite. Secundarly they profyt me in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they exerciſe my fayth, and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tefye my fleſhe and kepe me truly in my vocation.<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.</note> For why yf I do any benefite to my fryndes and to myne ennemys, and perceiue yt to come of a tranke and free hart, than may I well aſſure my ſelfe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my faith is lyuely and a true faith which makyth of damned ſinners the true children of god.<note place="margin">Ioh. 1. Gal. 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here is to be noted that good workes be theſe, which a man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuyng in Chriſt workyth in faith in hys lawfull vocation, after the ordena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and forme of the lawe of god. Contrary euyll workes<note place="margin">Euyll workes</note> and ſinnes be theſe which be donne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out fayth and with a fayned cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, truſtyng vpon them to por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fauore of god, the forgyue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:4729:11"/> of ſynnes, and the kyngdome euerlaſtyng, the which is cleane and directly contrary from oure chriſtian fayth. For our chriſtian fayth doth grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vs vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a more ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiall ſtone which is Chriſt,<note place="margin">The fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacion of our faith</note> the trew forgyuer of ſynnes, and oure only reconciler, which hath obteyned for vs thys grace, hath waſhed away our ſines, and hath deſerued for vs euerlaſtyng ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. This fayth makyth oure conſciences that they wauer not not doubt any thyng of the grace of god. For the properte of thys fayth is to quiet oure conſcience.<note place="margin">Rom. 5. what true faith is.</note> The trewe catholyke and lyuely fayth is thys whan a man fully perſuadith him ſelfe, and beleuith ſtedfaſtly, and nothyng doubth, that he hathe god pacified, and a moſte gentyll father to hym for Chriſtes ſake, to whom in all hys neceſſite, aduerſite, and in all his
<pb facs="tcp:4729:11"/> affayres as a childe to his father, he wholy committeth and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyth him ſelfe, putteth al his truſt in hym, callyth on him, ſekyng no ſuccoure, conſolation, nor good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes but only of him.<note place="margin">Act. 15.</note> This fayth purefieth oure hartes. This faith is always workyng through cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite, &amp; hath the holy gooſt whiche moueth vs and ſtyryth vs vp to follow the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of Chriſt, which hath left behi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſteppes of al good workes, and paciente in afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for vs to folow, ſaye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to vs. This is my commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that ye loue together as I haue loued you.<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.</note> You be my fryndes yf ye wyl do theſe thynges that I haue gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and taught you.<note place="margin">Ioh. 14. Ioh. 15.</note> He that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyth me wyll kepe my leſſons. I haue gyuen you exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, as I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue done to you, ſo do ye to youre ſelfes, by this you ſhal be knowen to be my deciples, yf ye haue loue
<pb facs="tcp:4729:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> one to an other. Agayne, he that takyth not vp his croſſe and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowyth me,<note place="margin">Luc. 19.</note> he is not my diſciple. Where there is no repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce nor any amendme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of lyfe,<note place="margin">
                  <p>No good fayth no good wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes.</p>
                  <p>Trewe faythe trew wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes.</p>
               </note> and ſtudy of good workes, verely there is no trewe fayth. Trewe fayth can not be with out good workes no more than a good tree wyth out fruyte, or the ſone with out hys heet, this is vndoubted. Therfore let euery man examine and ſerche hym ſelf well leſte he deceiue hym ſelfe. Many men there be whiche ſaye they beleue whan they haue no beleue, as it may apere by their vyciouſe &amp; wycked lyfe. For this is certai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, where ſo euer trew faith is, ther is alſo the feare of god, the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re is repentance, there a trew and a chriſten mannes lyfe folowyth, there the old ſynful man is put of and a newe put on.<note place="margin">Eph. 4.</note> For by cauſe this is the vertu and the operatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:4729:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> of our holy baptiſme, that fayth doth clene renue and tranſforme a chriſtean in to a new ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whych walketh not after fleſhe, but after the ſpirit. Rom. viii.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Then where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of god wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyth in vs good fruyte, and we begyne to followe the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of god our old man is not all mortefied ſtreyght waye, but wyld and wanton with her luſtes doth ſtryue agaynſte vs all oure lyfe long, and neuer ceaſyth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uokynge vs to ſyne, and euer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellyth agaynſte oure ſpirite, let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng &amp; hynderynge vs in all oneſt vertuys, wherby we be not able to lyue ſo vpryght after goddys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes as we wold. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whan oure ſynfull conſcience or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feare of death doth come vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not truſt to our workes, nor fynd any comforte therin, but (yf we wyll be ſaued) we muſte
<pb facs="tcp:4729:13"/> nedes cry w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy kynge Dauid. Enter not lord in to iugeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with thy ſeruant, for in thy ſyght no ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng fleſh ſhall be iuſtefied. Our good workes thoug they be neuer ſo holy and excellent yet the value of them is not ſuch, nether aught we to doo them for any ſuche pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, nether dothe god require them to be done of vs for that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that we ſhuld be iuſtefied and ſaued by them. For no man can truſte any thyng to hys workes, nether be they able to delyuer vs from oure death,<note place="margin">Our iuſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficacion only belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geth to Ieſu Chriſt.</note> that thyng only the workes of Ieſus Chriſte is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to do and nothyng els. Thys glory and honor is only dewe to him and to no man els, to be a Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,<note place="margin">Ieſus a ſauiour</note> that is by interpretation a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uior. For he o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly taketh away our ſynnes. iuſtifieth and ſauyth vs by hys workes and paſcion. This is hys office his worke and dewte
<pb facs="tcp:4729:13"/> only, for the whyche he was ſent hyther of his heauenly father and ours to doo. Therfore yf the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly workes and commandementes of god, can bryng no peace of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, than what ſhall a miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſynner do in the diſtreſſe of his temtation? whether ſhall he goo, whether ſhall he turne hym ſelfe? where ſhall he fynd help, and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coure, and comfort? ſo than yf we wyll loke for any ſaluation, we muſt firmely beleue and perſuade our conſciences, that oure ſynnes be pardoned vs, and clene taken away. But now howe ſhall we be ſo certefied in our myndes. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere in ſuche temtations a man muſt nedes ſet apart the lawe, and all hys good dedes that euer he hath done, al hys ſtrength, al his pouer, and merites, and let them all goo in this poynt. For here no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thyng can ſuccoure vs, but only
<pb facs="tcp:4729:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> the workes and paſſion of Ieſus Chriſt. And therfore we muſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pele from the lawe,<note place="margin">Appele fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lawe to the ſon</note> ſtreyght to the ryche &amp; mercyfull promyſe of oure father in his ſone Chriſt, as vnto a ſuer ſuccour and a ſanctuary of eternall ſecuritie and peace, and holde it faſt in a fyrme and a ſure fayth. And thus ſhall we fynde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forte and quietnes ynoughe, and more than we can deſyre, than ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſynne, nor death, nor hell ſhal not be able to hurte vs.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What the promyſe of god is.</note>The promyſe of God is this.</p>
            <p>Almyghtie God hathe promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vs damnable ſynners in his onely begoten ſone Ieſus Chriſt, with out any maner of excepcion or condicion of our owne merites clerely of his owne free grace and goodnes,<note place="margin">Hie. 31.</note> full remiſſion of all our ſynnes, his holy ſpirite, and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtynge lyfe,<note place="margin">Heb. 8.</note> and that he wyll e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer more be oure father, and that
<pb facs="tcp:4729:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> he wyll voutchſafe to receyue vs to his children, and gyue vs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall ſaluacion.</p>
            <p>Theſe be trewe, fyrme, eternal,<note place="margin">Heb. 9.</note> vnfallible, ſuer and ſtedfaſt God whiche is almyghtie,<note place="margin">2. L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and whiche can not lye hathe ſo promyſed to vs, and hathe ſworne depely by hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfe that he wyll performe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>This is the newe teſtament, &amp; the euerlaſtynge couenaunte of grace made to vs in Chriſte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt him and vs, and confyrmed with his blode, wherof his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes ſo greatly ſpeake of.</p>
            <p>Chriſt the ſone of God hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>firmed this teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by his death, and is a ſuer gayge or a pledge of this promyſe of God. The truth and grace of God is layde and re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſed for vs in Chriſte, in hym we be ſuer to fynde it, as God ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of his ſone Chriſt oure trewe Dauid in the pſalme .lxxxix.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4729:15"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 89.</note>
               <q rend="margQuotes">My trueth and my mercy ſhall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore be with him, and in my name his power ſhalbe exalted, he ſhall call me. Thou art my father my God, and the reſcuer of my health. And I ſhall ſet hym to be myne heare and fyrſte begoten, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunſe vp aboue al the kynges of the earthe. I ſhall euermore reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue my mercy to hym, and my faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full teſtament vpon hym. And I ſhall ſet vp his ſede for euermore, and his throne lyke the dayes of the firmament. And if his chldren tranſgreſſe my preceptes, and wyl not walke in my Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes I ſhall viſite and chaſtice theyr ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities with my rodde, and theyr ſynnes with ſtrypes. But I wyll neuer take awaye my mercy clene from hym, and my truth ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer fayle him. I wyl neuer breake my teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that I make, neyther wyll I euer go from my wordes
<pb facs="tcp:4729:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> that procede out of my lyppes. Ones haue I ſworne in my holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ſee yf euer I breake my a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poyntme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with my ſeruaunt Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyd, his ſede ſhall remayne for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and his throne lyke the ſonne in my ſyght. &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This promyſe is alſo redde in the .ii. Reg. vii.<note place="margin">2. Reg. 7.</note> Here in this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſy God ſpeaketh of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eternall kyngdom of Chriſt, in which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall mercy, peace, and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is, for in Chriſt he hathe repo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed &amp; layd vp his truth and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. Therfore in no other thynge can this promyſe of grace be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d or obtayned ſayue only in Chriſt. In him god hath promiſed to vs ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> frely through his mygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie mercie: Therfore who ſoeuer beleueth in Chriſte without any more a doo (to be bolde vpon it) he hathe all thynges, And though there be in Chriſtes kyngdome
<pb facs="tcp:4729:16"/> weyke and infirme ſinners, which ſlyppe &amp; fall many tymes, yet this priuelege &amp; prerogatiue they haue their ſinnes ſhall not be imputed to damnation. All theire offenſes be offenſes of children not of ſar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantes. We haue a ſalue conduct and a paſſeport through all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryls of death and damnacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And thoughe we fall neuer ſo heynouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly yet ſhal we not periſhe therfore, for our chriſtian fayth doth ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten vs vnto oure Dauid Chriſte that we be made one ſprite with hym. In Chriſte we haue the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of Goddes promyſe, and his mercy euermore to continue, oure heauenly father wyll not puniſhe his weake children in his wrathe for euer, but wyll chaſtice them w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fauour in this temporall lyfe, call vs agayne to repentaunce. Thus the grace of God ſhall euer abyde fyrme and ſtable, whiche we be ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er
<pb facs="tcp:4729:16"/> ſhall not fayle vs ſo that we be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leue this Dauid Chriſt to be oure kyng &amp; caſt all our truſt on him.</p>
            <p>And here is to be noted and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſidered where he ſayth.<note place="margin">Truth.</note> My treuth and mercy allways go with hym, yf it be his trewth, than it can not ley, nor deceiue vs. Yf yt be hys mercy and grace,<note place="margin">Grace.</note> than yt ſtandith not by oure workes nor the lawe, wherfore all theſe thynges ſhall happen to vs in Chriſte, and for Chriſtes ſake, which by hys wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes and paſſion hathe purchaſed and bought all thyng for vs.</p>
            <p>Eſay. lv.<note place="margin">Eſa. 55.</note> Bowe downe youre eare and come to me, heare me and your ſoule ſhall lyue, and I ſhall ſtryke a bergayne with you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall, the ſuer mercies which I promyſed to Dauid. Ierem. xxxi.<note place="margin">Ier. 31.</note> This ſhalbe the bargayne that I ſhall ſtryke with the houſe of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell. After thoſe dayes I ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:4729:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> gyue my lawe within theyr bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, and wyll write it in theyr har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,<note place="margin">Nota.</note> and I wyll be theyr God, and they ſhall be my people, for I wyl pardon all theyr iniquities, and wyll no more remember theyr of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences. &amp;c. So doth the apoſtle in his epiſtle to the Hebrues alledge the ſame place,<note place="margin">Heb. 8.10</note> where he proueth that this bargayne of grace are this newe teſtament betwyxt god and vs is now confyrmed and ſea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led vp by the death of Chriſt. And that god is now no more a ſtreyte iudge but a moſt tender father to all the faythful of Chriſt, and that he wyl pardone all their offenſes. Lykwiſe to the Gala. S. Paule callyth thys eternall bargayn of grace,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.</note> a teſtament that ſhal ſtand for euer, where as he wryteth. No ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> brekyth or dyſordenyth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyll or teſtament of a man beyng ones confirmed and ratified. Than yf
<pb facs="tcp:4729:17"/> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes ones made and confirmed, abyde firme and ſuer, how muche more the teſtament of god ones confirmed and ratified, ſhall abyde firme? Theſe teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes do proue euidently &amp; ſtrongly that goddes grace promiſed in Chriſte is firme and ſuer, ſo that now no beleuer ought ne ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doubt of the fauor of god and remiſſion of hys ſynnes.<note place="margin">we ought not to dought.</note> But vndoubtedly and conſtantly ought to ſtyke to this promiſe of god which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not nether ſhall be found falſe.</p>
            <p>What hart now is ſo hard or ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney that wyll not rele<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or be ſtyred vp by thys firme and ſwete pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of god, to take a bolde fayth and a confident truſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace and fauor of almyghte god beyng ſo promiſed to vs? Wyll not theſe wordes make vs certefied, yea &amp; alſo ſecure as yt were a bonde or a bargane, teſtament, promiſe,<note place="margin">Bonde, teſtamet, promyſe, mercy, an othe.</note> an
<pb facs="tcp:4729:18"/> othe, mercy. And all theſe doth no man whiche maye decyue vs, but god eternall promiſe our father in heauen, which is truyth hymſelfe.</p>
            <p>Yt is an horrible blyndnes in vs that whan god hymſelfe doth calle vs to hys grace, &amp; doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe frely to vs for his marcy ſake clere remiſſion of our ſynnes, and for the ſame purpoſe hathe ſent to vs hys only begotten ſone in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, to be a ſuer token or plege of hys heauenly fauor and grace, and yet we lene and hold more to our owne ſtynkyng workes than to the trew &amp; euerſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng truyth of god. Alas for pyte howe many pretious ſoules moſte pytuouſly haue be brought to deſperation, throughe theſe workes dooynge. The law only hath bene put forth vnto them, &amp; no thyng els beten into theire heades, but this, what god requireth of vs, howe great
<pb facs="tcp:4729:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſynners we were, what ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gaunce of God dyd fall vpon ſynne, what tormentes, what fyre and brym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone we ſhuld ſuffre in hell. But none taught the people faythful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the promyſe of God, the goſpel of Chriſte in the whiche ſorowfull and vexed conſciences of ſynners myght be refreſſhed and lerne the infinite and vnſearchable grace that God whiche of his vnknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en mercy hathe promyſed,<note place="margin">Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myſe is a gyfte.</note> that is to ſaye hathe geuen vs frely in Chriſt, with the whiche promyſes ſely conſciences myght be releued and confyrmed ſtrongly agaynſt all the gates of hell. We blynde and wretched wolde reward God with ours, and deſerue of hym all thynges that we had / we wolde not be in his det or daunger / we dyſdayned to haue his liberalitie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me freely vnto vs / and nothing wolde take of hym by grace. And
<pb facs="tcp:4729:19"/> that was the cauſe why Chriſte was not ryghtly preached but on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly Moſes:<note place="margin">what was the cauſe wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Moſes was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yd and not chriſt.</note> So it alwayes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to paſſe, when the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes onely be ſet forth, after the maner of the Iewes, and the promyſes of God nothynge ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of / there it can be none other but that mennes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences muſt nedes be vexed and diſquieted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> miſerable ſorowe and perplexitie ſo that they can receyue almoſte no conſolacion. But who ſoeuer wyll brynge men to God in dede, and wyll quiet theyr conſciences, muſt alwayes teache theſe two to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether the lawe and the promyſe / as the prophetes, Chriſte, and the apoſtles euer dyd.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The vſe of the law</note>By the lawe they brought men to the knowlage of theyr ſynful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, theyr vnworthynes, theyr in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie and vnabilitie to good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / theyr dutie what they ought
<pb facs="tcp:4729:19"/> to do / and theyr damnacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which therof folowed: And ſo broughte them to humiliate them ſelues be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore God / wherby they being iuſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſtroken with the feling of gods ryght iudgement, myght erneſtly forthynke them of theyr ſynnes / &amp; call for mercy. They taught not the lawe ſo as thoughe it were ynoughe to knowe what were to be done, or not to be done / or as thoughe of our owne ſtrength we coulde do good and eſchewe yll / and ſo by the lawe and by oure owne workes be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de iuſt before God / and put awaye ſynne. They taught not the lawe I ſaye for no ſuche ende nor purpoſe / neyther was the lawe gyuen therfore that we ſhulde be iuſtified therby be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God / but it was gyuen for this to requyre of vs all ryghtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes and to threten vs,<note place="margin">why the law was gyuen.</note> that by the requiringe of this rightuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<pb facs="tcp:4729:20"/> and we beynge nothynge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to perfourme it, we myght the better lerne therby our vnryghtu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouſnes and noughtines / and ſo fi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nally to acknowlage and confeſſe our owne wretchydnes, to then<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that beynge thus contryte &amp; humiliated in hart we might ſeke to Chriſt for ſocour the whiche by his workes and paſſion doth on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly iuſtefie vs.</p>
            <p>We be nothyng able to deſerue any ſaluacion by the lawe or our workes. That is an hygher and a more excellent thinge than that our rotten workes be able to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure. God hath promyſed to gyue vs that freely by his mercy for Chriſtes ſake, and doth gyue it of grace to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that beleue in Chriſt, as S. Paule to the Romaynes doth call euerlaſtyng lyfe the gift of God.<note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Gal. 3.</note> And lykewyſe to the Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lathians doth put a clere differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
<pb facs="tcp:4729:20"/> betwixt them, and ſheweth playn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly his mind of the law &amp; of the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myſe, howe they concure to oure iuſtificacion. Let vs weghe well his wordes, for al the weyght and fundacion of our iuſtificacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth lye vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. His wordes be theſe. <q rend="margQuotes">If our inheritaunce ſtande of the lawe than it ſtandeth not of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſe.<note place="margin">Marke.</note> But God dyd gyue it to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham. If the lawe had he gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs whiche myght haue iuſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fied vs, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our iuſtificacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might be of the lawe. But the ſcrypture hath wrapped all thynges vnder ſynne, that the promyſe myghte come by the fayth of Ieſus Chriſt to all that beleue.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And agayne in the ſecond to the Gal.<note place="margin">Gal. 2.</note> If our iuſtificacion ſayth he could come by the law, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt dyed in vayne. Therfore I ſaye where as men thus by the lawe were brought to the knowlage of
<pb facs="tcp:4729:21"/> theyr ſynnes, and ſo ſtroken with great ſorowe and heuynes of con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience for theyr ſynfull and vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous nature, than was the Goſpel put and ſet before them that is to ſay Grace promyſed vs in Chriſt. And than dyd they begynne to be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leue erneſtly &amp; to reioyce in theyr hartes truely for this grace pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſed in Chriſt, that God had gy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for Chriſtes ſake forgyue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of theyr ſynnes. Thus ſaynte Paule in the place afore recited, dothe comforte with trewe conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacion wretched and deſperat ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners for he leadeth them onely to the promyſe of God, and beateth that in to them, for therby onely our conſciences be cleane and qui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eted. And dothe teache the lawe &amp; gods commaundementes alſo, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortynge vs diligently to the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of good workes, and is not on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly content with that, but alſo doth
<pb facs="tcp:4729:21"/> ſhewe where and howe to come by the corage and luſt to do theſe good workes.</p>
            <p>Thus fyrſt they taught the law for repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce but ſtreyght after they ioyned withall the promyſe of God to brynge me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lege of the mooſt ryche grace of God gyuen and promyſed vs in Chriſte, teachynge withall where we ſhulde get the ſtrength to full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyll the commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, where oure ſynfull nature was not able to fulfyl it.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> In conſideracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of the Apoſtles euerywhere decla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red and ſet forth the excedyng and paſſynge ryches and treaſures of Goddes myghty grace whiche he hathe gyuen and promyſed vs in Chriſt, yf we beleue vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, and ſo forthe dyd lede wretched ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lawe to Chriſt. This great grace of God ſo offered they receyued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and enbraced great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb facs="tcp:4729:22"/> and thus beleuynge were paci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fied in theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences. The lawe doth threten and affraye, but than ſhe is not able to heale or comfort them beynge greued, or to dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them from theyr agony / wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore we muſt nedes flee to the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myſe. And there ſhall we fynde ryghtuouſnes, peace, lyfe, &amp; helth ynoughe. Hereupon S. Paule to the Gal. iii.<note place="margin">Gal. 3.</note> ſayth The lawe was but as it were oure ſcolemayſter vnto Chriſt,<note place="margin">The ende of the lawe.</note> that we ſhulde be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by Chriſt / for the lawe doth force vs, doth conſtrayne vs, doth call vpon vs, dothe manace vs, &amp; lyeth vpon our neckes, requiring of vs all maner of good workes, perfecte iuſtice, perfecte innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie of harte, perfecte feare and loue of God, and alſo of our neyghbour. But we of oure owne ſtrength be not able to acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plyſhe that which ſhe requyreth, &amp; thus ſhe dryueth
<pb facs="tcp:4729:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> vs to Chriſt, and is our ſcolemay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter vnto Chriſt. He tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> receyueth vs commynge to hym, helpynge vs, and gyuinge vs all ſuch thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that the law requyreth of vs / ſo that the lawe is not able to damme vs.</p>
            <p>For this cauſe S. Paule doth call Chriſte the ende of the lawe. Rom. x.<note place="margin">Rom. 10.</note> Or as S. Auguſtine doth expounde it the fulfyllynge of the lawe. He that hath Chriſt is iuſt, he that beleueth in Chriſte hathe all thynges which the lawe requi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth. Chriſte hathe reconſyled for vs God his father / he is our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator and euerlaſtynge preeſt he hath obtayned vs grace, the holy gooſt with all his gyftes, remyſſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of ſynnes, &amp; all maner of good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes with lyfe euerlaſtynge, he as Ieremye wryteth .xi.<note place="margin">Iere. 11.</note> dothe gyue vs a newe harte and a ſofte harte and the holy gooſt to moue vs for
<pb facs="tcp:4729:23"/> to do well. And where as yet we be partly fleſhly nor can not be all mortefyed in this body, nor tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly fulfyll the commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of God, there is he made oure wyſdome, our iuſtice and redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon, ſo that his innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie and all that euer he hathe is made oure by faythe / for after that we put on chriſte vpon vs, and after we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue in hym, there is no ieoperdie can hurt vs, thoughe we be neuer ſo weake and frayle, ſo that we do not walke purpoſely after our ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>petyte of the fleſſhe, and ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne ſtyll hedlonge in ſynne with our repen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taunce / for oftymes it happeneth that good and mooſt holy men do fall as well as other but yet they lye not ſtyll,<note place="margin">Good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do ſynne.</note> but get vp agayne, &amp; be ſtyll delyted withe the lawe of God inwardelye in theyr hartes, euer callynge for remyſſion of ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes by Chriſte, and optayne alſo
<pb facs="tcp:4729:23"/> the ſame which he deſyre. Al theſe thynges we maye ſe very well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in Abraham, for Abraham (ſayth Paule) is the father of all the faythfull beleuers in chriſte / therfore we haue in Abraham a clere figure and an example howe that a ſynner maye be iuſtified, &amp; what is the nature of chriſtiane fayth, what is the power, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie, and workinge of the ſame / and alſo how that our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences may be quieted, whether by fayth or by workes / therfore he that is the trewe childe of Abraham, that is a good man in dede, or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wolde be a trewe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre of chriſt, let him loke vpon Abraham his father, and there he ſhall ſe howe God dothe with vs, howe he tendereth vs, and howe we ought to do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne for hym, as Paule alſo tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs. Rom. iiii. Gal. iii. Fyrſte of all Abraham harde the great &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:4729:24"/> ryche promyſe of God ſayenge vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to hym, do not feare Abraham, I am thy defender, and great is thy reward with me. And afterward.</p>
            <p>In thy ſede all nacions ſhall be bleſſed, that is ſhall be delyuered from ſynnes, death, and maledicci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on and ſhall haue euerlaſtynge lyfe. This was glad tydynges to Abraham. And ſtyl dyd Abraham beleue this promyſe, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge yet moche greuyd with tro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bles and ſorowes. And ſo therfore was Iuſtified by this faythe and truſte that he had to the promyſe of God.<note place="margin">Nota.</note> Now this was .iiii.c. and xxx. yeares before the law was gy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen, and therfore was he ſauyd, not by the workes of the law, but by his fayth in God and in the ble<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſſed ſede whiche was promyſed hym. And no otherwyſe alſo muſt we al be ſaued, for ther is no other way nor meanes to come to helth,
<pb facs="tcp:4729:24"/> only the promyſe of God muſt iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyfie vs yf we beleue, and not the lawe nor no workes.</p>
            <p>Secondarly this fayth of Abra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ham that he hadde vpon Chriſte, made him a newe man, and cleane dyd alter his olde affeccions, and put in hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> newe cogitacions other<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wiſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this nature of ours hath, for he reioyſed onely in the lorde, and in hym taketh a meruaylous boldnes, he knoweth well that God is his father which in all his affayres, his affliccions and tro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bles wyll helpe hym, and is able to helpe hym, and thus truſtynge vnto Gods promyſe receyueth &amp; repoſeth hym ſelfe in the handes of God, with a bolde harte and a ſtronge confidence, doughtynge nothynge but that God wyll be mercyfull vnto hym, euen as any father wyll be to his owne natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall chyld, whome he loueth moſt
<pb facs="tcp:4729:25"/> tenderly, ſo then Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hauinge this fayth, went vp to the hyll, at the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God, to ſhewe his obedience &amp; offered his ſonne, for true faythe can neuer be with out good workes, but euer wyll be occupyed in the obedience of God Iac. ii. Gal. ii. In the meane ſeaſon Abrahams harte and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience was nothynge vnquietted for all that, but ſtyll quiet by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his fayth he had in Chriſt, for he was euer ſuer of the fauour and the loue of God toward him, wherfore S. Paule Rom. iiii.<note place="margin">Rom. 4.</note> full wel deſcribeth his whole thought and cogitacion, where as he ſayth that Abraham dyd neuer ſhrynke yet in his faythe, nor doubted in the ꝓmyſe of God, but euer ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge in his faythe, dyd gyue glory to God, knowynge well this that he which promyſed hym was able to performe it. And therfore he ſayth
<pb facs="tcp:4729:25"/> that it was imputed to hym for iuſtyce, that is for his iuſtificaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on / for this Abraham thought &amp; perſwaded hym ſelfe that God was almyghtie &amp; true of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſe which wolde not defeall nor deceyue his people. And yf he had ſo thought in him ſelf as now our papyſttes do teach, I can not tell ſuerly whether god loue me or no peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture he is not frendly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, nor caryth for me, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardyth me. &amp;c. Yf Abraham I ſay had thought on this maner, or had ſhrynked ſo in hys fayth, I thynke he wold neuer haue inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyd to offer vp his only ſonne, nor wolde haue bene perſuaded to go from his fathers houſe owt into a ſtrange lande, but rather wolde haue thought thus. It is good to be ſuer of that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath all redy, this I haue and am ſuer of, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is vnſuer, what ſhuld I kyll
<pb facs="tcp:4729:26"/> my onely and welbeloued ſone? who wyl gyue me an other? what ſhulde I goo out of myne owne houſe in to a ſtrange land I can not tell howe farre? what folyſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes were it? I wyll not ſo, I wyll tary ſtyll here where I am in my fathers houſe. Neyther wyll I be ſo cruell to my ſone for to ſlee him thus I ſaye he had thought yf he had not beleued conſtantly / but whan he went out ſo boldely and merely out of his fathers houſe into a farre and a ſtraunge coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre, and with ſo luſty chere went vp to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hyll with his ſone to offre hym vp to God, which no nature of man can do, for what naturall man can fynde in his hart to offre vp his ſone. Than by lyke he dyd only hange of the handes of god, onely dyd truſte vpon God, vpon his grace, vpon his helpe, nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g doubtynge in his conſcience but
<pb facs="tcp:4729:26"/> that God was able to performe all that he had promyſed, for why no doubtynge harte can be ſo wyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lynge to do as Abraham dyd, nor yet ones thynke to do it, ſo quyet was Abrahams co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience by faith in gods promyſe, that Paul in his epyſtle to the Rom. iiii. doth gyue hym an excellent prayſe therfore, that we all ſhulde marke it, and well beare it awaye. Abraham ſayth he neuer dyd ſhrynke in his fayth, but alwayes ſtronge in his beleuinge truſted ſuerly, why dyd he truſt ſuerly? bycauſe God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſed, for this he dyd knowe and was fully perſuaded, that God was trewe of his worde and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſe, what ſo euer he promyſeth he performeth of his grace, and is well able to performe it, for he is almyghtie, nor dothe not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſe for our deſeruynges but of his grace only,<note place="margin">Rom. 4.</note> that nowe we may
<pb facs="tcp:4729:27"/> be bold to truſte vnto it. For yf he ſhulde promyſe after oure deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynges, any thyng he culd neuer performe yt, for oure merites be none and nothyng worth, but he doth promiſe vs infinite goodnes in Chriſt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out our merites, only of hys pure grace and mercy. And therfore wryteth Paule Gal. iii. y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god promyſed Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſſyng, cccc.xxx.<note place="margin">The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe was made ere the lawe came.</note> yeares before the lawe of Moſes was gyuen, by cauſe that no man ſhuld ſo thynke that thys bleſſyng dyd ſtande of the workes of the lawe, or that he culd not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy thys fre promyſe and bleſſyng of god before he dyd fulfyll all the lawe of Moſes. Wherfore for the loue of god lett all good men here marke, that Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neuer fayled nor dyd ſhrinke in faith, nor neuer doubted at the promiſe of god, nor of the loue &amp; grace of god toward him. For ſo the holy goſt doth ſay
<pb facs="tcp:4729:27"/> that he had a ſuer perſuaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, mark well this. Yf yt were a perſuaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that he had, than yt was no opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, nor doubtyng that he had. But fully dyd truſte &amp; beleue, he went not thyther whether hys in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credulyte and doubtyng dyd byd him to goo, the whiche doubtyng our papiſtes haue taught vs, whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther thought he thus, whyther yt be true or not true I wyll do yt, but his conſience was fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded that it was true that god had promiſed, and that god wold be good and mercifull vnto hym, had forgyuen his ſinns, had iuſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyed him, and wold neuer forſake him nor abiect him, and after this lyfe alſo wolde gyue hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euerlaſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g lyfe for the ſede ſake that was pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſed hym, whiche was Chriſte. Yf god had ſayd thus to Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Here Abraham I wyl be merciful vnto the, I wyll forgyue the thy
<pb facs="tcp:4729:28"/> ſynnes, &amp; always be preſent with the and helpe the ſo on this condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that thou kepe and fulfyll all my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundmentes, thus I ſay yf god had gyuen him his promis vnder this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition of fulfyllyng his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes, then Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſience had neuer ben me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry nor quiet but always doubting of the grace of god &amp; forgyuenes of hys ſynnes, nor ſhuld bene cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne of his ſaluation. For thus he myght haue taught. I haue do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne all that I can w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all deligence to fulfyll goddes preceptes, yet I culde neuer fulfyll them ſo perfect<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye as I awoght nothyng lyke, wherefore thys promiſe of god is vncertane to me, nether I can tell whether I ſhall take yt or no, for bycauſe I haue not performed all that was inioyned &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded me and god dyd gyue me his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſe no otherwyſe but of this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
<pb facs="tcp:4729:28"/> yf I kept his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, and I am not able ſo to do, wherfore I am not ſuer whether he wyll gyue me theſe thynges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he promiſed. I can do nothyng on my part, and therfore how can he kepe his promiſe with me, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what hope can I haue nowe of helth. Yt is but loſte labor all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I go about, thus I ſaye yf god had promiſed hys bleſſyng vnder this condition to Abraham, then he myght wel haue deſpeared, but now he addyd no ſuch condition,<note place="margin">The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſe cam without any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicion.</note> &amp; all becauſe we ſhuld not doubt, but that his promiſe remanyth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſuer and ſtable. And this it is that god requireth only of vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhuld neuer doubt nor queſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>one of his fre grace, but to be bold and truſt vpon yt, that he is a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng father to vs, and we be his children. But we culde not be ſo bolde of thys grace of god yf any
<pb facs="tcp:4729:29"/> ſuche condition of fulfyllyng the law were gyuen w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all, as yf thou kepe my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes wel, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhalt thou haue thy ſynnes forgy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Therfore yt is neceſſary that the promiſe of this bleſſyng ſtand without all conditions, and with outt all reſpect of oure workes or meretes, but only in the fre grace of god, for or els we culd neuer be ſuer of yt nor certane but always in doubt and myſtruſt, For yf the remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our ſinnes ſhuld ſtand in the fulfyllyng of the lawe, then our fleſh beyng ſo weyke &amp; frayle, and not able to fulfyll the lawe, how ſhulde we know and be ſuer that god is good to vs or that we were in the fauor of god, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhuld thynke that he were an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gre with vs, becauſe we neuer ful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyll his commaundmentes as we ſhuld do. And thus the fre promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of god ſhuld ſtand voyde and in
<pb facs="tcp:4729:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> no effecte. For why no man were able to obtayne yt. But thankes and prayſe be to the faythfull lord the father of our lord Ieſus chriſt and ours, the father of mercy, and the god of all comforth wiche ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng mercy vpon vs and tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our weyknes hath not byldyd oure helth and ſaluation vpon no ſuch brykell and weyke fundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as vpon our workes and our ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyllyng of the lawe, for ſo we culd neuer be ſaued But the fundation that we be groundyd vpon &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uale agaynſte the gates of hell,<note place="margin">The fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacion of our hope.</note> is the great grace and mercy of god in his ſone Chriſt. For in him god hathe promiſed vs all the remiſcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of oure ſinnes, and euer laſtynge lyfe. Thys promiſe is only and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone all our comforth that we may bouldly truſt vpon. So thus you ſe how god promyſeth vs remiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our ſinnes and lyfe euerlaſtyng
<pb facs="tcp:4729:30"/> not vnder any condytion of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng and fulfyllyng the law, but he gyuyth yt frely of his fre grace I ſay, only &amp; alone throw Chriſte, &amp; not for no workes of ours. And therfore he gyuyth yt frely, with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out any condition of our workes. Bycauſe the promiſe myght ſtand fyrme and ſtable, that is, that we may be ſure of the fauore of god &amp; of the remiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our ſynnes, doub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyng nothyng therin, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng we be neuer ſo much ſynfull in oure nature, &amp; vnworthy wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, that euery beleuyng chriſten man may ſay with Paule. Thys I knowe and is vndoubted, that nether deth nor lyfe nether a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gels,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> nether prynces, nor poteſtates, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges neygh, nor thynges to cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nether heyght nor depnes, nor no other creature is able to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate vs from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue of god whiche is Ieſus Chriſte oure lorde. Here
<pb facs="tcp:4729:30"/> may we playne ſe that Paule had a bolde and a confident truſte of the forgyuenes of his ſynnes, and of his helth to come, plentuouſly perſuaded of the grace of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde hym or elles howe could he ſo feruently lerne, reioyce, and tri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>umphe in ſprite agaynſte all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures bothe in heauen and in the worlde, ſo omnipotently deſyryng them all, beynge ryght ſuer and certayne that nothynge neyther aboue nor benethe coulde anoye him, and why? bycauſe he beleued in Chriſt, and was ſure of the mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy of God towarde hym through fayth / and therfore was his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſo quiet and triumphant. And euen ſo maye euery chriſten man lykewyſe take the ſame co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and the ſame mynde in hym ſelfe.<note place="margin">Marke.</note> Howbeit no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can do this vnleſſe he put awaye all reſpecte of his owne merytes and workes
<pb facs="tcp:4729:31"/> and only truſt vnto the free mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and grace of God, which grace is gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs onely throughe chriſt and not throughe oure ſelues. Tit. iii.<note place="margin">Tit. 3.</note> that notwithſtandynge yet theſe good workes of ours do folowe and ſprynge out of this faythe and promyſe of God. And loke there where as they do not folowe and maye folowe there is no trewe nor lyuely faythe, but on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly a deed and barayne opinion of faythe, but where this trewe and lyuely faythe is, there is workyd miracles and thynges farre pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſynge the poſſibilitie of naturall workynge. For as ſaynt Paule ſayth / we receyue the holy gooſt not by our workynge but by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the goſpel,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.</note> this holy gooſt wyll not ſuffre vs to doubte after the papiſtes faſſion, or as they wold haue vs, nor to fere as their ſeruyle ſprite dothe, but with a
<pb facs="tcp:4729:31"/> bolde truſte cryeth in oure hartes to God abba father, and wytneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth with oure ſperite that we be the chyldren &amp; the heyers of God and felowe heyers with Chriſte, that we maye be glorified toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with hym. And as Paule to the Epheſians ſayth,<note place="margin">Ephe. 1.</note> they that be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leue in Chriſte be ſealed vp with the holy ſpirite of promyſe, the ſpirite we haue as a pledge or an erneſt peny of our inhereditaunce and poſſeſſion which we haue got and be redemed vnto.<note place="margin">The holy ſpirete is our pleas</note> Therfore with all fayth and truſt we muſte euer loke vpon the promyſes of God, and vpon Ieſus Chriſt on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And ſo in this promyſe of God our conſcience may fynde comfort and peace plentie, but in our wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes we ſhall fynde none. And ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore marke wel this text of Paule and kepe it well in youre remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce, where he ſayth.<note place="margin">Rom. 4.</note> Rom. iiii
<pb facs="tcp:4729:32"/> Abraham had this promyſe gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to hym &amp; to his ſede that he ſhuld be the heyre of the worlde, not for his workynge after the lawe, but for his byleuynge in fayth / for yf they whiche belonge to the lawe be the heyers, then is fayth voyde and the promyſe of none effecte / for why the lawe worketh angre, by reaſon that yf there were no lawe, there were no tranſgreſſion, therfore is the inheritaunce gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by fayth as by grace frely, bycauſe the promyſe muſte ſtande fyrme &amp; ſtable to all the ſede of Abraham. Dayly experience and practyſe in our trobles and dyſtreſſes decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that no man be he neuer ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly can quyet his conſcience by his workes.<note place="margin">Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</note> Oure ſynnes and death be more greuous enemyes vnto vs than that we be able to ouer come the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by oure owne dedes and deſeruynges / we muſt haue an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:4729:32"/> maner of meanes to that, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is our faythe receyuynge and holdynge the promyſe of God in Chriſte. And ſo that is able to con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quere the mighty ferſnes of ſynne and death. This fayth receyueth and ſtyketh to moſt ſure and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall thynges that can neuer fayle vs and not to oure workynges, but to the great grace of God, to Chriſte him ſelfe, to his workes &amp; his deſeruynges and to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſe in Chriſte, brefely to all that Chriſte hathe, or is worth / whiche thynges be moch greatter, higher more ſtable, and magnificall, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our capacities is able to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hende.<note place="margin">Remedy i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> Therfore whan any temta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion commeth we muſt not loke to the lawe and oure workes, but ſettynge all them a ſyde, we muſt runne and crepe to the croſſe of Chriſt, we muſt ſeke for helpe and grace by chriſt, &amp; hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bli muſt know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lage
<pb facs="tcp:4729:33"/> oure faultes. And thoughe oure ſynnes be neuer ſo great or greuous, thoughe the feare and temptacion of deathe be neuer ſo horrible, yet we muſt ſtyll ſtyke to the promyſe of God, and ſuerly muſt truſt, and doubte nothynge, that oure ſynnes be forgyuen vs for Chriſtes ſake accordynge to the promyſe of God, without any deſeruynges of ours: &amp; that God is oure father, and we ſhall lyue with hym for euer and euer. The workes &amp; paſſion of Chriſt, which be of great and infinite and omni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>potent power ought more to ſtyre vs vp to truſte well on God that he wyll be euermore to vs a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyful lord, than our ſynnes ought to fraye vs, for the grace of God in Chriſte is moche ſtronger and more able to deliuer and helpe vs than our ſynnes be to condempne vs. Roma. v.<note place="margin">Rom. 5.</note> And this grace of
<pb facs="tcp:4729:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> god doth not hang of our workes for than yt ſhulde be vncertayne, but yt ſtandyth fyrme by grace of fayth through Chriſt, with out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny regarde or reſpect of oure wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng. And this is done by the ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular prouedence of the great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly loue of god toward vs, by<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe our iuſtyficatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld ſtand firme &amp; certayne by faythe, ſo that no man nede doubt of the fauor &amp; marcy of god toward him, yf this grace &amp; promiſe ſtand in the hand of god, than is yt ſuer, ſo that we can not doubt of the remiſcion of our ſynnes. But yf they ſhuld ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in our owne hand and ſhuld hang of our ſelfes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſhuld always be vncertane by cauſe we were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer able to deſerue ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, not of ſufficient ſtrenght to fulfyll the lawe. But after that we returne &amp; referre our ſelfes in Chriſte alone, and in the promiſe of god through
<pb facs="tcp:4729:34"/> Chriſte than be we ſayfe and ſuer ynough by cauſe god hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of hys voluntary grace frely, and hath founded his promiſe by the fayth in Chriſte, to thentent yt ſhall ſtande fyrme &amp; certayne. And therfore I ſayd the kyngdome of Chriſt to be a kyngdome of ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te and peace,<note place="margin">Chriſtes kyngdom is a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>curitie. Eſa. 32.</note> as the prophites do deſcrybe yt, In this kyngdom we haue peace and moſte ſuer ſuccur, ſo that there is nowe nether ſynne death nor hell can feare vs. So dothe Eſaias alſo .ix. call Chriſte the prynce of peace wooſe prynce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is large &amp; greate,<note place="margin">Chriſt the prynce of peace.</note> and whoſe peace ſhall neuer haue ende. In Ieremie alſo .xxiii. god doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe vnto Iſraell, that is vnto all beleuers in Chriſte a boadde of iuſtice, a kynge whiche ſhall rule wiſely, and ſhal execute iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and iuſtice in earth &amp; vnder who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iſraell ſhall dwell boldly, theſe
<pb facs="tcp:4729:34"/> thynges be in the ſpirituall kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt in the which there is true &amp; ſpirituall ſecuritie, where as euery chriſten mans hart hath peace with god through fayth in Chriſte, in the whiche kyngdome nether ſynne can damne vs nether death ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> kyll vs, nor hell can ſwa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>low vs. For god is with vs and fedyth vs, and defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyth vs as his ſhepe. Therfore who ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be againſt vs? And Eſaias agayn .xxxii.<note place="margin">Eſa. 32.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the holy gooſte, ſayth he, ſhall be powred from aboue (y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was whan Chriſt begane his kyngdome) tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the worke &amp; fruyte of iuſtyce ſhall be peace, and the kepyng of iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce ſhall be ſilens and ſecurite for e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer and euer. And the peple of god ſhall dwell in goodlynes of peace and in houſes of truſte. All theſe thynges do nothyng els but ſigni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fie that Chriſtes people i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome ſhall be all good, quiett, at
<pb facs="tcp:4729:35"/> reſt and mery, which ſhall haue a quiet and a glad conſciens, beyng euermore ſuer and certaine y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god is fauorable to them for Chriſte, which doth delyuer vs from all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyls w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out any doubt. I pray you what can oure aduerſarys bryng aganiſt this, or how ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they mayn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyne their errors in the face of the worlde.<note place="margin">The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.</note> Here I haue prouyd and taught out of the fundation of the worde of god that no faythfull be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuer in Chriſt can doubt or ought to doubt of the fauor of god and of remiſcion of his ſynnes, and that his conſcience may thorwly be cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tefyed that god is fauorable vnto hym, which wyll pardone all his fautes, for Chriſt in whom we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue and whiche wyll iuſtifye vs, and gyue vs euerlaſtng lyfe with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out any doubt.<note place="margin">Obiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</note> Here our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res can haue no thyng to lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt this doctryne or to ſubuert
<pb facs="tcp:4729:35"/> this foundacion, but one refuge they haue, and when we brynge ſcryptures agaynſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: what ſaye they, the Lutherians, ſaye they, brynge ſcryptures for them, but they muſt expounde ſcriptures as our fore fathers dyd.<note place="margin">An a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwer</note> I anſwere a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gayne, we do not denye ſo to do, for we maye do it well ynoughe. And I may ſaye with S. Cyrillꝰ,<note place="margin">Cirillus</note>
               <q rend="margQuotes"> we kepe the fayth of our fathers &amp; of the church ſo farre as we ought and vſe theyr interpretacions ſo moche as they requyre.</q> But the chefeſt of the auncient fathers of the churche do agree in the ſame matter no other wyſe then we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounde it / therfore what do theſe holy workers brynge for them the churche.<note place="margin">Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine de predeſt. 11</note> Saynt Auguſtyne one of the moſt catholyke and godly doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tor of them all in his boke whiche he writeth of the predeſtinacion in the .xi. chapiter ſayth in this wyſe.
<pb facs="tcp:4729:36"/>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Truly where as the apoſtle in his epyſtle to the Rom. wryteth theſe wordes. Therfore is oure inhery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce gyuen vs by fayth through grace bycauſe the promyſe myght ſtande fyrme and ſtedfaſt, I mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, ſayth he, that men had rather loke on theyr owne infyrmite tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the firmite and ſtedfaſtnes of Gods promyſe.</q> But here thou wylt ſay, I can not tell nor do not knowe the wyll of God of me, wel the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doeſt thou knowe thyne owne wyll of thy ſelfe, yf thou doeſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, he that ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth let hym take hede that he fall not. Therfore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomoche thou knoweſt neuer no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his wyl, nor thyne owne wyl, then why ſhulde not a man rather put his truſt &amp; hope in that which is more certayne than in that whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is leſſe certayne. But ſay they agayne, heare where it is ſpoken, yf thou beleueſt thou ſhalte be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,
<pb facs="tcp:4729:36"/> one of theſe is required of vs, the other is offered, &amp; that whiche is required of vs is in vs, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in God. And why, I pray you is not bothe in Gods power both that whiche is required and that whiche is offered? for do not we as well deſyre God to gyue vs that whiche he requyreth as well as that he offereth? do not the bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers alſo deſyre hym to encreaſe theyr fayth: Do they not deſyre alſo for the vnbeleuers that they may haue fayth, ſo that God only muſt be the begynner and encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer of fayth. In lyke maner is this to be taken. Yf thou beleueſt thou ſhalt be ſaued, &amp; this, yf you mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the workes of the fleſſh with ſpirit, ye ſhall lyue: for in lyke caſe here one is requyred, thother is offered. Yf you mortefie (ſayth he) the workes of fleſſhe with ſpirite ye ſhall lyue / then to mortefye the
<pb facs="tcp:4729:37"/> workes of fleſhe by ſpirite, this is requyred, the other then is offered vs that we ſhuld lyue / what then therfore ſhal we not ſaye that this is the gyfte of God to mortefie the workes of the fleſſhe bycauſe it is requyred of vs to be done? God forbede that any perteynynge to the grace of God ſhuld ſo thynke. This is a damnable errour of the Pelagians, whom as the apoſtle in his wordes folowynge doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fute ſayenge, who ſoeuer be led w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſpirite of God they be the chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God. Leſſe we ſhuld thynke this mortefyeng of the fleſhe came by our ſpirite, but by the ſpirite of God, of the whiche ſpirite of God the ſame apoſtle ſpeaketh more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer. All theſe thynges ſayth he, worketh one alonly ſpirite, diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butynge to euery man his gyftes ſo as it pleaſeth him, amongſt the whiche gyftes alſo he rekeneth
<pb facs="tcp:4729:37"/> fayth / ſo then lyke as this morte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyenge of the fleſſhe notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge it be requyred of vs is the gyfte of God, euen ſo is fayth alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very gyft of God though neuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>theleſſe it be requyred of vs (yf we wyll be ſaued) to beleue, for theſe thynges bothe be commaunded vs of God, and alſo be the gyftes of God. To the entente we ſhulde vnderſtande, that both we do the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and yet it is the gyfte of God that we doo them / ſo as the ſcripture ſheweth by Ezechiell the prophet. And I (ſayth almyghty God) ſhal make you that you ſhall do them what can be more playne? Marke ye well this place of ſcrypture (ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll brethren) and ye ſhall ſe that God promyſeth, he wyll make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to do ſuche thynges that he wyll haue done. And there he bryngeth forthe no merites of theyrs, but moche wyckednes, ſhewynge and
<pb facs="tcp:4729:38"/> declarynge therby that he geueth good for euyll in that that he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them brynge forth afterward good workes, cauſynge them to do his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes. Alſo in the .lxxxviii. pſalme he ſaythe in lyke maner. Lyfte vp your hartes for he whiche promyſed, wyll per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, ſo as he hathe performed many thinges alredy / for the truſt that we haue in hym we haue it not in our merites but only of his mercy. No man can be ſtronge in this lyfe but onely in the hope of Gods promyſe / for as concerning our owne merites we be meruay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous weke,<note place="margin">we be wea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke in our ſelues / in Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſe ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g</note> but as concernyng the promyſe of God we be ſtronge.</p>
            <p>And in the .lxxxxviii. pſalme he ſayth / where is ſecurite &amp; peace, he anſwereth agayne, truely none in this lyfe but onely in the hope of the promyſe of God. S. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe<note place="margin">Ambroſe.</note> in the fyrſt boke de vocat ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ti.
<pb facs="tcp:4729:38"/> &amp;c. wryteth yf no man (ſayth he) wyll breake or diſpyſe a mannes wyll or teſtament, as ſayth the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, nor alter it. Then how can it be that Gods wyl and teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſhulde be broken in any thynge.</p>
            <p>It carieth alwaies and euery day is fulfylled that the lorde promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to Abraham without any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicion, &amp; gaue without any lawe. By this ſayenge of Ambroſe it may wel appere that the promyſe of the newe teſtament, that is to ſaye that God wyll be mercyfull vnto vs, wyll forgiue our ſynnes, wyll gyue vs the holy gooſt, and wyll make vs ſafe, that thys pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſe I ſay doth not depend of no condition of the lawe, for frely yt comith only of grace, be cauſe we ſhulde neuer doubt of hys grace &amp; fauor toward vs. And what other thyng menyth S. Ambroſe wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng vpon Paul, where he ſayth
<pb facs="tcp:4729:39"/> ſo oft, that we be ſauyd before god by fayth only &amp; alonly. Loke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his come<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taris of the Rom. iii.iiii.ix.x, Cap. loke alſo .i. Cor .i. and Gal. i.iii.v.<note place="margin">Theophi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lact.</note> Theophilactus alſo Rom. iiii. wryteth in lyke ſort. In ſomuch ſayth he it is euedent, that the lawe bryngyth nothynge but angre therfore had Abraham hys Iuſtice &amp; inheritance gyuen hym, bycauſe that all ſhulde go by gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce. Wherfore than ſeyng that all thynges now do ſtand in the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and in the mercy of god, ſo that he is bound now not to worke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hys Iuſtice, then what ſhulde let vs to thynke but that all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges be certane and ſtable what ſo euer he dothe, gyue, or promyſe. Now yf blynde hipocriſe here ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect again that Paule in his place ſpekyth only of Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; therfore that thyng co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernyth none els but hym, but we muſt ſeke oure helth
<pb facs="tcp:4729:39"/> and iuſtification otherwiſe. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere agayne. Not ſo, For ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Paule callyth Abraham there the father of all the beleuers and in him propoſeth to vs all the true meanes how all men bothe before the cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myg of Chriſte and after the cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myg of Chriſte muſte be Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. And therfore this text of Pau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le doth as well pertayne to vs all, for it is writen and propoſed vnto all vs.<note place="margin">Rom. 4.</note> Euen as S. Paule in the very ſame chapiter writeth. This is not writen for hym only, ſayth he, that it was imputed to him for Iuſtice, but for vs all, to whom it ſhall be imputed for Iuſtice. bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng on hym which reyſed vp fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death oure lorde Ieſus Chriſte, which was gyuen for our ſynnes, and reyſed vp agayne for oure Iuſtification.</p>
            <closer>Amen</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
